<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at S. Maries in Oxford vpon the feast of Epiphany concerning the true comfort of God his Church truly millitant and apologie of the same. Ianuary 6. 1589. By Edwarde Hutchins Maister of Arts, and fellow of Brazen-nose College in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Hutchins, Edward, 1558?-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03906</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14015</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104318</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840056</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840056</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4527</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03906)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4527)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 250:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at S. Maries in Oxford vpon the feast of Epiphany concerning the true comfort of God his Church truly millitant and apologie of the same. Ianuary 6. 1589. By Edwarde Hutchins Maister of Arts, and fellow of Brazen-nose College in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Hutchins, Edward, 1558?-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Ioseph Barnes, and are to be sold in Pauls Church yeard, at the signe of the Tygres head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1589]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sold by T. Cooke, London. Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4527:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4527:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT S. MARIES IN OXFORD VPON THE FEAST OF EPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHANY CONCERNING THE TRVE COMFORT OF GOD HIS CHVRCH TRVLY MILLITANT AND APOLO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Ianuary 6. 1589.</p>
            <p>By Edwarde Hutchins Maiſter of Arts, and fellow of Brazen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſe College in Oxford.</p>
            <p>IMPRINTED AT OXFORD BY Ioſeph Barnes, <hi>and are to be ſold in Pauls Church yeard, at the ſigne of the Tygres head.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4527:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4527:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL MAISTER THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAS EGERTON, <hi>ſollicitour to her</hi> Maieſtie. Grace and peace in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>ONSIDERING with my ſelfe (Right Worſhipfull) on the one ſide, the painfull and profitable paines of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and godly ſet forth from time to time: but neuer more fully and clearely then in this our accepted day: (to God be the glory) ſo that in that reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nothing can bee written, that hath not bin written: and on the other ſide, mine own exility or rather nothing to all; in ſelfe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (as one ſpeakes) more needing to reade than to write. I was perſuaded &amp; ſet, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit no more then I haue doone, to the preſſe. Notwithſtanding, I may not bee mine owne nor follow my ſelfe: but as I haue heretofore beene ouer-ruled: ſo haue I been now againe, at the earneſt and importunate ſute of my dear frinds in Chriſt, to yeelde this ſermon to the print. Whereupon as in generall I deſire the fauourable iudgement of the reader: ſo of ſpeciall duetie (in token of my thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full minde) I am boulde to dedicate it to your Woorſhippe, humblie crauing your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable
<pb facs="tcp:4527:3"/>
acceptaunce of the ſame, and of that trueth and true comfort, which I haue therein, though according to my manner and ſmall talent, yet faithfully deliuered. And ſo in wiſh of all proſperitie in Chriſt vnto you, I committe your Woorſhip and all yours, to the Almightie, who bleſſe you in all your waies and ſend you many good daies, to his good will and pleaſure, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips euer in Chriſt to commaund. <hi>E. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4527:3"/>
            <head>It is written in the 7. Verſe of the 4. Chapter of the ſong of Salomon. <hi>Thou art al fair my loue, and there is no spot in thee.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING</hi> heretofore at three ſeueral times (Right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful &amp; dearly beloued in Chriſt our dear Sauiour) ſpoken out of this place of this text: of the name &amp; appellation of Chriſts Church here named by the name of a loue: of the reaſons of that name: actiue and paſſiue: <hi>actiue, respectu fidei, respectu facti: paſſiue, respectu natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae, reſpectu gratiae, quoad eſſe</hi> and <hi>bene eſſe:</hi> of the appropriation of this name: of a caueat that it was not to bee taken by way of excluſion: as though the church were not the loue of God the father &amp; of the holy Ghoſt: but yet by ſome way of ſpecialty appropriate to Chriſt, becauſe he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone of all the three perſons was <hi>promiſſus</hi> and <hi>miſſus</hi> to witnes the loue of God vnto her &amp;c. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alſo handled the commendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this loue, that ſhe is firſt commended to be faire: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be fair actually and preſently: Thirdly in generality, for better ſifting whereof yet I ſtood vpon three negatiues: Firſt, that ſhe is not here commended to be al fair, either doctrinaliter, as though ſhe could not erre in matters of faith, or moraliter, as though ſhe did not er in matters of fact: or in reſpect of her condition and ſtate in
<pb facs="tcp:4527:4"/>
the worlde; thus far proceeding, it remaineth nowe that I come to the affirmatiue generall, that where you haue hard how ſhe is not, I may at length reſolue how this loue is ſaid to be fair, to be al fair. In which reſpect the principall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion and propoſition is this: that the Church this loue of our Sauiour hath preſent and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect beuty: is faire and all faire in reſpect of her Chriſt, in whom (though not by grace infuſed, as heretofore you haue heard) yet of grace and therefore gratis (as the ſchoolemen haue wel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined:<note place="margin">Gratia non eſt gratia vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo modo, ſi not ſit gratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ita omni modo. <hi>Pſal. 32.2. Iob 141.</hi>
               </note>) of grace &amp; therfore gratuitally or elſe no way of grace, (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> truely ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued) imputed therefore, no ſtain may be found. For albeit in conſideration of her frailty and weaknes for the time of this life or rather her warfare, againſt the world, ſinne and ſatan ſhee doe cary her wounds and doth oftentimes faile and defile her ſelfe: though the law in that reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect bee the glaſſe of God,<note place="margin">Anſel. ſupr. <hi>8.</hi> cap. epiſt. ad Rom.</note> that diſcouereth her ſpots vnto her: ſo that her ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt wraſtler, her beſt <hi>Iacob</hi> might ſtand in fear of his moral halt, of his fal, if he ſhould regard the ſame in courſe of iuſtice: Yet the lawe is anſwered by the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel:<note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.19. 1 Ioh. 3.8. Luc. 15.5.9.</note> in the goſpell by Chriſt, in whom the godly are, as ſtrong though weak, as rich though poor, as clothed though naked: as recouered though loſt: as free though bound: as ſound though ſore, ſo cleane though foul: for in this point we muſt diſtinguiſh the ſtate of them that are Chriſts, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4527:4"/>
in Chriſt, which may be conſidered two waies. Either a <hi>poſteriori</hi> or a <hi>priori: à poſteriori quoad fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, à priori quoad faedus &amp; pactum: quoad factu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> in reſpect of duty performed &amp; deeds of life they are not al fair but foul &amp; that,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1. vlt. Iob. 9 3. Iob. 14.4.</note> 
               <hi>peccato</hi> eyther <hi>acto</hi> or <hi>contracto</hi> (as the ſchoolmen wel ſpeak:) by ſin therefore perſonally committed or at leaſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally deriued. And thus this loue is as ſhe ſaith ſhe is: I am not all fair but black ye daughters of <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> euen as black as euer were the tents of <hi>Kedar;</hi> which is true,<note place="margin">Cant. 1.4.</note> not only in reſpect of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction but natural corruption and corrupt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as truth bears it: where as yet <hi>quoad foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus &amp; pactum,</hi> which ſerues to purge, either <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatè</hi> (as infantes who belong to the kingdom of chriſt:) or <hi>medi ante fide</hi> (mediatly by faith) as they adult, ſhe may ſay as ſhe ſaid:<note place="margin">Cant. 1.4.</note> I am not foul but faire, comly, al fair, ye daughters of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> euen as comly &amp; al as comely, as euer were the curteyns of <hi>Salomon:</hi> &amp; in fine anſwere her Chriſt of her ſelfe as Chriſt by way of comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation ſaith of her vnto her heere,<note place="margin">Eſa. 9.6.</note> in <hi>Salomon</hi> a type of him, the King of <hi>Salem</hi> Prince of peace: <hi>I am al faire my loue, and there is no ſpotte in me.</hi> The truth and proofe whereof appeareth to be true two waies: <hi>ex parte ſponſae</hi> and <hi>ex parte sponſi: ex parte sponſae,</hi> and therefore to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in ſcripture ſhe is compared to a groat:<note place="margin">Luc. 15.9.</note> but yet not loſt but found: accepted, faire and al fair in the eye of that gracious woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (the very mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror
<pb facs="tcp:4527:5"/>
of grace) that took the pains to light the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of mercy, to ſweepe, to ſeeke, to finde, to ſaue the ſame: to this purpoſe ſhe is compared to the man of <hi>Ierico</hi> but yet not foul but faire, by the <hi>Samaritanes</hi> grace not ſore but made ſound: to this purpoſe ſhee is compared to a chicken but yet not vnfethered or naked but couered with the winges of the Henne:<note place="margin">Luc. 13.34.</note> in concluſion: to this point ſhe is compared to a Lamb but yet not ſo fleeced but couered and clothed with the white wool of fauour and mercy 'fair and al fair, free from al ſpot in Chriſt her ſpotles lamb, ſpotles though man,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.29. Mat. 1.20. &amp; 27.4. <hi>Bern. in pſal. qui habitat. ſer.</hi> 9. Ioh 1.9. Eſa. 49.6. Mat. 9.12. Mat. 9.12. Ier. 30.23. Luc. 2.30. Ioh. 11.25. Oſ. 13.14. Luc. 2.30. Mat. 1.21. <hi>Tertul. de carne chriſt. lib. pag.</hi> 26. 1. Cor. 1.30.</note> that ſhe might be al faire without ſpot. Secondly, this general commendation ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be true <hi>ex parte sponſi:</hi> and therefore to this purpoſe Chriſt in Scripture is called her <hi>lux:</hi> her light therefore he is: and <hi>ergo</hi> darkneſſe may aſſoone be found in the light; her <hi>medicus,</hi> or rather <hi>medicina</hi> &amp; <hi>ſanitas:</hi> and <hi>ergo</hi> ſicknes may aſwel be in health: her <hi>vita:</hi> her life therfore: and therefore death may aſſoone be found in life: her <hi>ſalus,</hi> her ſafety, as appeareth by the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and <hi>ergo</hi> deſtruction may as eaſily be found in ſaluation: her redemption and <hi>ergo</hi> bondage may aſwel be in liberty: her <hi>iuſtitia</hi> and <hi>ergo</hi> ſin may aſſoone be found in iuſtice (which yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be) as ſhe be charged with any ſin, with any filth or foulenes in Chriſt Ieſus; in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus? For (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaks in another caſe) ſo ſay I in this: that this loue of Chriſt is not
<pb facs="tcp:4527:5"/>
only <hi>eccleſia Chriſti</hi> but <hi>Chriſtus:</hi> not only <hi>ergo</hi> to bee conſidered as the church of Chriſt, but as Chriſt: as Chriſt, who aſwel may be ſaid to ſtray though the way; to be deceiued though wiſdom:<note place="margin">Ioh. 14 6. Luc 11.49. Mat. 23.34. 1. Cor. 24. Baruc. 3.37. Ioh. 14.6.</note> to er or to ly though truth; to be infirme, though omnipotent, though the very arme of the power of God; to be foule, though pure, though purity it ſelfe, as his true church to be foul (conſidered in him:) in him? in whom her old man is deſtroied ſinne drowned, ſatan anſwered and her infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſo remoued,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.33.34.</note> that he cannot charge her with any ſinne, with any ſtaine or foulnes. A miſtery, a paradoxe I confeſſe to fleſhe and bloode, that one and the ſelfe ſame ſhould be foul and ſo faire: ſubiect to ſinne and yet ſo fair, as al faire; al fair, becauſe free from al foulenes, free from al ſinne: But yet ſo it is: and where reaſon doth not or cannot, yet faith perſwades it: faith which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth in Chriſt, not only the grace of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to pardon, but alſo of perfect imputation of his iuſtice to iuſtifie al them, that are by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of grace incorporate into him:<note place="margin">In his booke called, dux peccatorum.</note> and not only by nature (as <hi>Granate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſis</hi> wel ſpeaks) one with him as man but by grace alſo at one with God by him: who in him &amp; for his ſake forgiues and forgets the ſinnes of them that are his, yea as though they had neuer ſinned. In which reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect albeit the diuel would, yet can hee not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them: or if hee doe preſume (as hee is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſpirit) yet the godly may ſoone cut
<pb facs="tcp:4527:6"/>
him of and quit themſelues in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iſa. 11.8.9. Mat. 16.18.</note> in whome they are quit from ſinne, from all vncleanneſſe. Nay in this point the ſpirit of adoption doth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the ſonnes of God, that their ſinnes are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in Chriſt his ſonne, who was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for their ſin:<note place="margin">Rom. 8. v. 3. and 32.</note> and that by his ſufferings their ſinnes (as an old writer ſpeakes, though darkly, yet ſcholaſtically, and fitly) haue <hi>ſuum eſſe</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>malè eſſe:</hi> they haue therefore their maner of being without euil beeing: becauſe they are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away (as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> wel ſpeaks) <hi>vt non obſint, licet ſint:</hi> that therfore they be not hurting, though they haue their kind of being: or (as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſpeakes) <hi>quoad morſum. i. mortem, licet non quoad morbum:</hi> and al: becauſe ſinne cannot bee mortal to them,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> though ſin in and of ſelfe nature mortall, bee within them. Nay, aboue al this to ſet foorth this matter more fully: in ſpirituall warfare, when the godly are grieued with touch of conſcience for the foulneſſe of their imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and infirmities, the ſcripture it ſelfe doth thus yeald them the truth, their comfort, to the truth of this text; as for example: the foulneſſe of the ſinne of intemperance may trouble the ſoul of a <hi>Noah:</hi> but yet the fairenes of Chriſt, his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and abſtinence: the foulnes of the ſin of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience may greeue the conſcience of a <hi>Iob:</hi> but yet the fairnes of Chriſt, his patience &amp; paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: the foulnes of the ſin of murther and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion may diſquiet the ſoule of a <hi>Dauid:</hi> but
<pb facs="tcp:4527:6"/>
yet the fairenes of Chriſt, his loue and charity: the foulnes of the ſinne of ambition may mooue the Apoſt: to dreame of a primacy: but yet the fairnes of Chriſt, his meeknes and humility:<note place="margin">Eſa. 42.1. Mat. 18.11. c. 4.11.29. Mat. 26.70.72.74.</note> the foulnes of the ſin of ſelfe-loue and reſpect made <hi>Peter</hi> in his frailty to forſwear himſelfe, to ſay, to ſwear, to ſwear with a curſe that he knew not Chriſt, but yet the fairnes of chriſt, his gratious loue and pity:<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23. 1. Pet. 2.2.</note> the foulnes of the law of the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers may torment a <hi>Paul,</hi> any godly man: but yet the fairenes, the ſatiſfaction of Chriſt may be and is through faith a ſufficient ſtay againſt al temptation grounded vpon the foulnes of his imperfection whatſoeuer. To be ſhort: wher the godly are any way ſhort of themſelues; where ſatan obiecteth to the church, to this loue her want of obedience, her fouleneſſe, for ſupply of fairnes, ſhe may ſay (as once S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaide) <hi>quod ex me mihi deeſt vſurpo ex viſecribus domini:</hi> ſhee might aſwell anſwere to the courſe of this text, Auoid ſatan: for I am not ſo foul but that I am fair and al fair in the bowels and bloude of my Chriſt;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.59</note> in whoſe mercy my merit (mine frely becauſe it is his mercy that his merit is mine) I am purged from al ſin &amp; <hi>ergo</hi> al fair: if therefore thou canſt laye any thing to the charge of my Chriſt: eyther folly where he is my wiſedom: or infirmity where he is my ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth:<note place="margin">Damaſcen. orthod. fid. li. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> or guile wher he is my Doue: or pride where he is my humble la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b: or malice, where he is my loue: or any work
<pb facs="tcp:4527:7"/>
of darknes wher he is my light: or any foulnes, any ſin, where he is my <hi>ſanctus ſanctorum,</hi> my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of holyes, not only <hi>ſanctificatus ſecundum car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi> but <hi>ſanctificans quoad diuinitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orig. <hi>1.</hi> part. homil. xi. ſuper. nun. d. Tert. de car. chriſt. pa. <hi>33.</hi> Jbidem. De noctur. illuſionibus. collat. <hi>22.</hi> cap. <hi>9.11.12.</hi>
               </note> (as one wel ſpeaks) not only ſanctified according to the fleſh but ſanctifieng according to the power of his godhead: or (as <hi>Origen</hi> ſpeakes) <hi>qui ſanctus eſt non efficitur:</hi> who is a ſaint not made a ſaint: or (as Abbat <hi>Theonas, qui ſanctus eſt,</hi> nay not only that, but <hi>immaculatus:</hi> not onely a ſaint as the godly now be, but a ſaint without ſin (which the godly for the time of this life cannot bee) then charge me with ſin: otherwiſe as verily as chriſt my Chriſt, was foule and al foul, becauſe ſin for me:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5. <hi>Ciril. tom.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 235.</note> ſo am I not foul but fair &amp; al fair: righteous al righteous, becauſe the righteouſnes of god in him, whom thou canſt not charge with any ſin. Indeed if I were left to my ſelf, my feet are foul but yet auoid ſatan, wher my chriſt hath waſhed them: of my ſelfe my wounds are filthy, many &amp; mighty but yet auoid ſatan, wher my chriſt hath clenſed &amp; cured them: truth it is, my ſins are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, great and greeuous but yet the grace of my Chriſt, is an almighty grace; greater and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then they be; in whom their foulnes &amp; filth is purged away &amp; their greatnes come to nothing. Thus dearly beloued the church, this loue may comfort her ſelf, though foul by the wood yet (as one ſpeakes, an vnknowen autor) fair and al fair by her all comely crucifixe that died vppon the
<pb facs="tcp:4527:7"/>
wood: though foul in her own folly, yet al fair in her wiſdom: though foul in hir own frailties,<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Zach. 14.11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mich. 4.11.12.13. Iob. 8.34. <hi>Ciril. tom.</hi> 2.111. <hi>Bern. in Epi. ſerm.</hi> 1.</note> yet al faire in her might: though foule in her owne bondage &amp; captiuities, yet al fair, becauſe al free in her freedom: though foul in her ſins, yet al fair w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſpot in chriſt her ſpotles paſcal, once &amp; but once ſlaine to make her clean fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al her ſins, and foulnes. From al foulnes; as any may eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, if ſhe do but refer her ſelfe to the croſſe of her paſchal: thither, where ſhe may behold her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone &amp; ful acquittance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al ſin, from al her foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: thither, where ſhee may leape into the very ſide of her chriſt as into a wel and waſh her ſelfe faire and al clean in his blood,<note place="margin">Damaſcen. orthod. fid. li. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> the water of life y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alone ſprang out of his precious ſide, that heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain, to repreſent her al faire: thither, wher ſhe may run betweene the armes of her ſauiour, ſpred vpon the tree to embrace, to couer her fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all her foulnes, from all her infirmities: thither where (as one ſpeaks the ful comfort, to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe and proofe of this text) ſhe may waſh her foul head in the blood of his head, her foul hands in the blood of his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, her foul feet in the blood of his feet, her foule ſide in the blood of his ſide: her foul hart in the blood of his hart:<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.34. Reuel. 1.5. Mat. 26.28. Eph. 25.26.27.29.</note> her foul bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the pure, precious blood that coloured his body from head to foot: and her ſoul in his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſoul, yet preſſed to the very ſorrowes of hell for the filth of her ſins, to repreſent her al faire. Thus the church truly millitant, the godly may
<pb facs="tcp:4527:8"/>
anſwere the diuel in al trial of conſcience to the truth of theſe words; that ſhe is al fair. Which is indeed the cheefe felicity and hap of the church, that in al ſatans attempts ſhe is ſo able by faith to couer her ſelfe with the white garmentes of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.13.</note> by faith ſo to ſhield her ſelfe, as in chriſt her plenty to deny al want:<note place="margin">Col. 2.3. 1. Cor. 3.11.12. 1. Cor. 10.3.4. Eſa. 8.14.15. Cor. 2.12.32.34. 1. Cor. 2.8. 1. Ioh. 2.2.2.</note> in chriſt hir morning ſtar, to deny al darkneſſe: in chriſt her precious pearle and treaſure to deny al vilenes: in chriſt her foundation and rock to deny al weaknes: in Chriſt her glory to deny all ſhame: in chriſt her purgation and acquittance from ſin to deny all filthines and blame, that otherwiſe in courſe of iuſtice, iuſtly therfore might be imputed to her, in his goodneſſe to deny her foulnes, to defie the diuel and al hee can againſt this commendation that ſhe is not al fair. So much the more doe I maruel at them, and blame them, that teach in this behalfe diſcomfort for truth, nay (I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid truth) deſpeyre for comfort. That the church this loue of our ſauiour is not otherwiſe fair and al fair then by the inhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t grace, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of duty, &amp; that this imputed beuty in tru account, is no way real but imaginary: and <hi>ergo</hi> do not onely deny it but cry out againſt it. For anſwer to whom the proofe of the negatiue here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tofore hath prooued,<note place="margin">Prou. 20.9. Iſa. 41.29 &amp; 53.12. 1. Ioh. 11.</note> that ſhe is not actually, no, neyther can poſſibly for the time of this life bee ſaid to be fair, al fair in reſpect of good life; but that ſhe is foule: foul, becauſe ſteined with ſinne:
<pb facs="tcp:4527:8"/>
with ſinne: as <hi>Leuchettus</hi> wel noteth vpon the maſter of the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, his <hi>3.</hi> book. <hi>Diſt. 27. quaeſt vnica,</hi> according to the ſcripture. Whereupon it followeth, that where ſhe is here commended to be fair and al fair: and that not only for the time of the next life: (as S. <hi>Bern.</hi> would haue it: and truly, though ſomwhat reſtraintly:) but alſo for the time of this life, as the word approueth: &amp; yet that cannot be by infuſed, that it muſt needs be true by grace alone and grace onely imputed. Which imputation is not <hi>res opinaria</hi> but <hi>ſolida</hi> (as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſpeakes in a like caſe) no imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation therefore (as they write and as of late I haue ſeen the point charged in priuate ſchroles, which are abroad:) but a point of truth, and as real as was the imputation of our foulnes, of ſin to our Chriſt: who was not counted a ſinner, nay ſin in the cauſe of his church by imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though by only imputation. For the goſpel is no fable but a trueth: euen the woorde of Chriſt: as therefore the worde of this loues wiſedome:<note place="margin">1. Cot. 1.24. 1. Ioh. 2.2. <hi>Ciril. tom.</hi> 3. 108 6. Rom. 5.1.2. Eſa. 2.2. Act. 10.36. 1. Cor. 1.30. Ioh. 14.6. Ioh. 17.17.</note> for chriſt is her wiſdom: as the word of her reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: for chriſt is here peace: as the word of her righteouſneſſe: for Chriſt is her iuſtice: as the word of her life, for chriſt is her life: ſoo to make al theſe comforts good and this commendation true, it is no les then <hi>verbum veritatis,</hi> the word of truth: for Chriſt is truth: who ſpake the truth general of the word, when he ſpake to the father thy word is the truth. And what is the truth ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial
<pb facs="tcp:4527:9"/>
of the goſpell, if this be not that truth: that the church, this loue is al faire &amp; freed from her foulnes, not <hi>ex propria dignitate</hi> but <hi>ex imputata dignatione:</hi> not of ſelfe deſert therefore but of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerued, of imputed mercy, whereby Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came bound to free her, and foul, by his foulnes to beutifie, to make her al fair. For the truth is alike in reſpect of Chriſt &amp; his church: betweene whom through grace thence hath been euer, is and ſhal be ſuch intercourſe and change, ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication or rather communion by gratuital vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; no way but by imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which whether it be reall or not reall, true or not true, becauſe only imputed, I dare &amp; I do put it to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of any that haue any conſcience to conſider of truth. Thus <hi>ergo</hi> as really &amp; verily, as Chriſt was accounted for vs accurſed, though God bleſſed for euer: a ſinner a very diuel as the diuel himſelfe could teſtifie of him: as he was reputed among the wicked and died as a malefactor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the wicked, where yet he did neuer hurt, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer brake the law of loue but being loue it ſelfe performed both tables of loue: ſo is it true in the goſpell of grace to the comfort of all, that are within the compaſſe of the couenant of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting mercy and fauour, that they are no more wretched then the ſeed of the bleſſing, their bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: <hi>eccleſia</hi> (ſayth <hi>Ireneus) eſt ſemen Abrahami:</hi> the church is the ſeed of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> bleſſed <hi>ergo</hi> in Chriſt that ſeede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that ſeede of the
<pb facs="tcp:4527:9"/>
bleſſing: no more <hi>ergo</hi> wretched by the foulnes of life, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the ſeed of the bleſſing, their bleſſing: no more vnholy, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy one of god:<note place="margin">Mar. 5.7. 1. Cor. 1.30.</note> no more are the godly to be charged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſin, then iuſtice, the iuſtice of God, then Chriſt, their iuſtice, whom many did but none iuſtly could charge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſin any way; but only in reſpect of grace, in reſpect of the merciful ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of his heauenly father, who preordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in and of his goodnes to ſaue man:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Damaſ. orth. fid. l.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 1. 1. Ioh. 4.19. Deut. 7.7 &amp; 10.15. <hi>Iraen. ad here li.</hi> 5. <hi>pag</hi> 323 <hi>Baſ. inſo.</hi> 48. <hi>Damaſcen. orthod. fid. li.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; li.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. 1. Cor. 13.4. Heb 9.14. Gen. 3 6. <hi>Orig. ſupr. leuit. homil.</hi> Rom. 5 12.3. ca. 3. <hi>a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble place.</hi> Gal. 4.3. <hi>Tertul. adu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Iudae. p.</hi> 131. <hi>Anſel ſupr.</hi> 1. Cor. 15.</note> and to that end to ſatiſfie iuſtice. Which where it could not be done but by obedience as infinite in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as ſin was in offence: and therefore not by any creature but by very God: nor by god on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: becauſe God was and man had offended: and <hi>ergo</hi> as by very God of very God, ſo by very man of very man: and yet not by any man but by a man without ſinne and offence, that he himſelfe might not need, but by his patience and paſſions in his manhood, worke the ſaluation of man by the power of his godhead; I eaſily find man ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in miſerable caſe and yet vnder the lawe <hi>quoad culpam &amp; reatum:</hi> or els quitte <hi>à culpa</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>à culpae reatu,</hi> in the imputed obedience of Chriſt, who alone was God and therefore able: and made man &amp; <hi>ergo</hi> apt to be mans mediator, by taking mans ſin vpon him: mans at the firſt by voluntary choiſe, al mens in the firſt man by hereditary right, no way Chriſts (the <hi>2. Adams</hi> the <hi>2.</hi> for the <hi>1.</hi> ſake, man pure from ſin to make
<pb facs="tcp:4527:10"/>
this his loue al fair,<note place="margin">Bern. in dom. in ramis palm. ſer. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> though all foul by reaſon of ſin) whether by action or inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but by mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, not putatiue (as our aduerſaries blaſphemoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe inſinuate in the point of the goſpell) but ſcriptural: real therfore and true, though impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue; nether is the church truly millitant only al fair in Chriſt her meſſias and mediatour,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.30.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was without ſin, <hi>quia nunquam peccauit</hi> (which <hi>Hugo de ſ: victore</hi> doth note to haue bin the iudgement of ſome in his time) but alſo <hi>prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter impeccantiam</hi> (as the commentator vpon <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcen</hi> ſpeaks) or rather,<note place="margin">Anſel ſupr. cap. <hi>8.</hi> epiſt. ad Rom.</note> 
               <hi>quia fint impeccabilis,</hi> as moſt of the ſchoolmen vſe to ſpeake: not only <hi>erg.</hi> bicauſe he was not but alſo becauſe he could not be foul, he could not ſin. For in Chriſt there was no ſin,<note place="margin">Ber. ſerm. de paſſ. dom.</note> nether could there be ſin, <hi>quoad actum quoad habitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> or <hi>ſomite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi>) as the phraſe of the ſchols is) neither was nether could he in truth be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with ſin in effect or affect, in act or poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, beeing like man but yet the firſt man in this point before he did fal: pure <hi>ergo</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin: or like man after his fal,<note place="margin">T. Acq. vpon the <hi>5.</hi> of the <hi>2.</hi> to the Cor. lect. <hi>5.</hi> Tert. de car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne chriſt. lib. pag. <hi>27.</hi> Tert. in the ſame place and page.</note> not only <hi>erg. in ſtatu</hi> but <hi>in rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> (as <hi>Hugo de vict.</hi> well ſpeakes) but yet like him in al things <hi>ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>carne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccati,</hi> in reſpect <hi>er</hi> of the fleſh of ſin (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> wel ſpeaks &amp; tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (or rather ſinful fleſh (as the Apoſtles expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> point more warily:) but no way <hi>ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carnis,</hi> according to the ſin of the fleſhe, whether it were of omiſſion or commiſſion: committed outwardly, conceiued inwardly or contracted
<pb facs="tcp:4527:10"/>
lineally fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Adam.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſ. ſerm de humana chr. generatione.</note> So much the better ground hath this faire loue of Chriſt, of this her general comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation: becauſe ſhe is faire &amp; al faire only &amp; wholy in him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Damaſ. orth. fid. li.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 27 Ioh. 1.29. Reu. 5.8. <hi>Ciril. tom.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 48. Rom. 5. <hi>Tertul. de. praeſc. haeres. pag.</hi> 87.</note> who neither did neither coulde ſin, being appointed to ſaue her fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin: who <hi>ergo</hi> neither was nor could be any way foule, beeing that Lamb of God, ſlain from the beginning ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, at length vppon the croſſe viſibly to take away the ſin of the world: of the world, that is, of the elect: of the elect: whoſe ſinnes were his: his? which yet were not his by deſert but by loue, by loue &amp; not by inherence but by impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation only.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.2. Heb. 9.12. Iob. 3. Ioh. 8.24. <hi>Damaſcen. orthod. fid. li.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 27. 1 Pet. 2. Ioh. 1.</note> This is the goſpel &amp; to this purpoſe the Apoſtle is ſo plaine and expreſſe that oft I fal to a wonder at them, that wil needs imagine this to be but an imagination, and ſo eaſily can as they thinke and ſo commonly doe, without cauſe or probability in their books and late fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſchrowles reuile and declaime againſt this heauenly and moſt euident doctrine as not only ſome way improbable but abſurd in al diuinity, yea (and in <hi>Campians</hi> argument) in natural re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But (by your good leaue &amp; patience, though ſomewhat darkely yet in a worde and as I may plainly) to ſtand vpon the folly of their reaſons, which they take to bee reaſon: they goe about by philoſophy to confute diuinity or rather by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry, cauillation and ſlaundering to keep vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the trueth, which yet will haue the conqueſt and the victory It is abſurde (ſay they) in al di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity,
<pb facs="tcp:4527:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in philoſophy and nature to cal any thing white or blacke, faire, or foule, by the whiteneſſe or blacknes, by the fairnes or foulnes, that is not in it but without it. To reſolue therefore the church to be faire, al faire by the faireneſſe and beauty of Chriſt, in him and not in her or hers but becauſe imputed to her. For the ground of which their argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I anſwere firſt, that albeit the moſt proper be, yet that al true predications be not drawen from inherence. College walles can anſwere ſo much to their ſhame, that can no better obiect. <hi>2.</hi> I anſwere that this their argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is grounded vpon a miſconſtruction of our article or rather a wilful cauil or ſlander againſt the truth, where thy cannot confute our trueth. For we neuer defended this loues beuty &amp; faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to bee onely eternal and without her. For though the grace of this loue be twofold: the one preſent: the other future and to come: though by grace preſent, ſhe be alone fair and al fair in the grace of her Chriſt; not in her but without her: without her, and yet hers by faith, which appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth and applyeth his ful beuty vnto her as her owne, as by mercye wrought for her, ſo through fayth imputed vnto her for her owne:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Damaſ orth. fid. li.</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 10 Gal. 5.6.</note> though this be thus, yet this former beuty is not idle but actiue, the root of a ſecond for faith cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth loue and loue ſheweth it ſelfe by good life: and in reſpect of that life, in ſcripture, for the time of this life ſhe is counted faire, called iuſt,
<pb facs="tcp:4527:11"/>
iuſt: Yea and that according to the rule of phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy (as in this caſe they vrge) by iuſtice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent, by iuſtice performed of her: called iuſtice yet but not as iuſtified or iuſtifiable by the law,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc. 1.6. Gal. 3.22.</hi> Mandata dei facta de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putantur qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> od quicquid, non fit, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcitur.</note> as they would haue it, but rather and truely (as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> defined of it) becauſe ſo accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the goſpel of grace, which accounteth that for done, which man wanteth of frailty, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnfeinedly, and God pardoneth of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious goodneſſe and mercy: and thus the laſt time I noted that the church this loue of Chriſt is faire euen by inherent iuſtice, to the ſhame of them all, that ſay and vrge vntruely and falſly, that we, againſt al diuinity and ſenſe, defend the iuſtice of the godly, this loues beuty to be mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly externall and without her. <hi>3.</hi> I aunſwere by waye of iuſt condition and demaunde: what if it were otherwiſe in philoſophy, yet what is that to diuinity? If otherwiſe in nature? Yet the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is not alwaies neceſſary from nature to ſcripture? For (to keepe my ſelfe within my compaſſe) firſt of all, touching predications: <hi>theologica ſcientia,</hi> the Scripture hath ſuch, as philoſophy, as nature cannot admit, no nor <hi>ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malis homo</hi> perceiue or conceiue at al. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: in the point of incarnation which is (the very <hi>radix &amp; fundamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſtianae religionis,</hi> as the fathers wel cal it, <hi>verbum carofactum eſt:</hi> the word became fleſh: which is, as the ſchoolemen wel cal it, <hi>inuſitata predicatio:</hi> an vnuſual man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:4527:12"/>
of predication: but, what? Shall this very root of religion be cut off? The very grounde of chriſtianity bee ſhaken? Shall this bee falſe in ſcripture (the word of truth) becauſe there is not like example in all philoſophy or nature to bee found that may iuſtifie the ſame? As againe in the point of Chriſts paſſion (a principall article of the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) <hi>Deus gloriae crucifixus eſt,</hi> which is alſo, as they wel cal it, <hi>praedicatio communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> vnuſual, true yet by communion or vnion <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minitatis &amp; Deitatis,</hi> of the manhoode and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head in one Chriſt: as (in concluſion) among the reſt is this commendation of this faire loue of Chriſt (grounded vpon the two former) that ſhe is faire and al faire, not in <hi>ſe ipſa</hi> but in <hi>ſuo spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo:</hi> euen as chriſt was foule &amp; al foul, not in <hi>ſeipſo</hi> but in <hi>ſua ſponſa:</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe therfore was al fair in him as he was al foul in her: which is <hi>praedicatio inu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitata</hi> but yet <hi>vera, vera</hi> though <hi>imputata.</hi> But what? Shal theſe, the very groundes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of true chriſtianity be falſe in ſcripture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the like examples of predication to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſame, are not to be found in all philoſophy and nature? Abſurde. Howebeit I aunſwere by way of retorſion: that our aduerſaries them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues confeſſe how that this their conſequence is nothing from philoſophy to diuinity, from na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ſcripture. For otherwiſe (to demaund of them all) what becomes of their falſe named ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice or vſe of the ſame. Of their ſacrifice? For
<pb facs="tcp:4527:12"/>
in that they ſay there is ſomething round, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing white &amp;c. But not by inherence, not by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or rule of philoſophy or nature (eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as al pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts by catholick conſent do except of accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in the caſe of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where it doth not (as they ſay) <hi>ineſſe:</hi> why then will they meaſure the predications of diuinity by nature and philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy (they in general holding this for diuinity, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt al truth of true philoſophy? touching the vſe of their maſſe if al bee imaginary that is by imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then how liues the very ſoul of their religion? How doe their maſſes profit not onely the liuing but alſo the dead? But to adde a third point: all our aduerſaries graunt that there is a double iuſtification: and in both they all graunt and muſt defend the pointe of imputation. In the firſt iuſtification they ſaye and holde that infants and new conuertes (immediatly depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) are iuſtified and ſaued alone by the grace of Chriſt imputed: and in this reſpect they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and conſequently defend that propoſition of <hi>Luthers</hi> or rather principall principle of the ſcriptures, <hi>ſola gratia ſine operibus iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat &amp; iuſtificatos ſeruat:</hi> ſo <hi>Bunderius,</hi> ſo <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kius,</hi> ſo <hi>Cocleus,</hi> ſo <hi>Coſterus,</hi> ſo others, ſo all doe ſaye and defende, that bee of any account: why then doe theſe late men declame thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt imputation? Touching the ſecond iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation &amp; mean to glorification they hold that the merits of ſaints triumphant (which they cal the
<pb facs="tcp:4527:13"/>
churches treaſure (are imputable and imputed to ſaints not only liuing but departed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> popiſh pardons &amp; ſatiſfactions are grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded: but if this were true, why is imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? but thus it is, it muſt be truth in caſe of error whatſoeuer they imagine to be truth: they haue frewil &amp; free tongs to affirm, wher in proof they faile. Nay (as in diuerſe other pointes) ſo in this the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues they diſproue as you haue heard: and may more truely (as trueth requireth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clame &amp; cry out againſt their own fancies in the point of imputation, which tende to maintaine errour and hereſy) then againſt vs, who (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the trueth of the goſpell) flee from our owne folly and fouleneſſe to the booke of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to the goſpel; and therein to the Grace of Chriſt. in whom our nakednes onely and wholy is couered and the church this loue is faire and al faire and hath no ſpot or ſtaine that may bee imputed to her. In concluſion if any man looke in <hi>Harding, Roffenſis, Cocleus, Gratian,</hi> the cenſure of <hi>Colen,</hi> yea the <hi>Rhemiſh</hi> teſtament or the like authors or bookes: he ſhal find theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions among them and in them, that <hi>aliena fidei</hi> (as ſome ſpeake) <hi>or fides eccleſiae</hi> (as others ſpeak) doth ſaue an infant: and, that <hi>ſatiſfactio v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius valet pro alio:</hi> that the ſatiſfaction of one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailteh another. But if imputation bee not reall but imaginary, how can this ſtand? Where are the very ſinews, the ſoul of popiſh religion? Here
<pb facs="tcp:4527:13"/>
they cannot anſwere themſelues and for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and therefore I anſwere for them and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: that this their imputation is but an imagination:<note place="margin">De incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione verbi.</note> and what they doe vtter falſly of Saintes, that doe I truely pronounce of Chriſt the ſaint of al ſaints (as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> well calles him:) that the church millitant is fair and alfair not by the imputed ſatisfaction of any but onely of him, in whom ſhe is wholy faire, where of her ſelfe ſhe can no way be faire (as <hi>Pelagius</hi> drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) no nor in her ſelfe, by grace infuſed, bee all fair for the time of this life. Wel and wel did hee know this who was as faire as any man, a man after the very hart of God: &amp; yet ſo foul that he knew not how foul he was: <hi>dilicta quis intelligit? Ab occaltis delictis munda me domine?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.12.</note> O Lorde who knoweth his ſins? His foulnes? Lorde <hi>ergo</hi> cleanſe me from mine vnknowen foulnes? Wel did he know this, who was as faire as euer man was and yet ſo foul,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Cor. 5.</hi> T. Acq. vpon the ſame lect. <hi>1.</hi> Look alſo Cip. in tract. de ſingulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taie cler. pag. <hi>599. S. Paul. ad Ro. Gal. &amp;c 2. Cor. 8. Mat. 27.28.</hi>
               </note> that rather al foul then any waye faire: and <hi>ergo</hi> ſtoode in feare not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſome but of all his workes. Well and very wel did he know this who was ſo faire, that hee could ſay: <hi>nihil nihil conſcius ſum</hi> and yet coulde ande: <hi>in hoc tamen iuſtificatus non ſum.</hi> Oh howe wel did hee knowe this that taught ſo fully that man is iuſtified and ſaued not by works but fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, through faith in Ieſu Chriſt, whoſe pouerty auaileth only by imputation to enrich, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to glorifie, his paines to eaſe, his handes
<pb facs="tcp:4527:14"/>
to looſe,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24. Mat. 26.28. Eph. 1.9.10.11. Epeſ. 2.5 6.</note> his ſtripes to heal, his death to quicken, his bloodſhedding to clenſe them al and al faire, that in gods mercifull purpoſe haue portion in him and are apointed to be ſaued by him. Why but that were no iuſtice (ſay they) to account one iuſt, becauſe another is iuſt: the church, this loue all faire becauſe her Chriſt is al fair. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to them that thus argue, that although it ſtand not with the reaſon of the naturall man,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.20. Rom. 5.25. 1 Ioh. 2.1.2. and 4.10. <hi>Ber. in ſer. de paſſ. dom. T. Acq. vpon the</hi> 3. <hi>of the</hi> 2. <hi>to the Cor.</hi> Phil. 2.8. Rom. 5.6.8. Ioh. 3.16. Epheſ. 2.4. 1. Ioh. 4.10. <hi>Dam. orth. fid. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. 1. Ioh. 3.5. Rom. 4.25. 1. Pet. 2.4. Gal. 1.4. 1. Tim. 1.15.</note> yet ſtandes it with faith: which faith, which fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth iuſtice ſatiſfied in Chriſt for this loue, and this loue quit by the meriting mercy and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful merit of Ieſu Chriſt, which God accepteth for a ful &amp; thorow recompence of and for mans ſinne and offence. And albeit God were iniuſt, if he ſhould repute man for iuſt: iuſt? yea without deſert: yet where he conſiders not man in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe but in his dear ſonne Chriſt, who of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and grace perfourmed for man til it came to the very death, what the lawe demaunded of man: Gods mercy and iuſtice are both apparent &amp; manifeſt. For no cauſe there was but loue that moued him to accept man to fauor, who by ſinne had ſo diſpleaſed him: and yet of iuſtice or rather iuſt loue and mercy he accounteth them for iuſt, that belong to Chriſt his ſon, who being <hi>dilectus à patre immeritò nos dilexit:</hi> (as <hi>Ciprian</hi> well ſpeaks <hi>de baptiſmo Chriſti:</hi>) and vpon the tre took their perſon and ſtate vpon him and ſpared euen to ſpare himſelfe ſpared not, euen to ſpende his harts ſweet blood to repreſent this true church
<pb facs="tcp:4527:14"/>
his loue,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.9. <hi>Ber. in ſer. do paſſ. dom.</hi> Act. 2.23. Rom. 10.4.</note> faire and al fair in the eies of his heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father, who of his mercy had appointed him to work ſuch a wonder of mercy. So is it ſaid, that chriſt is the fulfilling of the law to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue: the fulfilling of the lawe? the law <hi>ergo</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not charge them with ſinne, with any foulnes:<note place="margin">Gal. 3.10.</note> in him <hi>ergo</hi> we are fair &amp; al fair: ſo is it ſaid, that we are the rightouſnes of god in him: the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God cannot be charged with ſin,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21.</note> with any foulnes: in him <hi>ergo</hi> we are fair and al fair: ſo is it ſaid that Chriſt is the Lambe of God that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away the ſin of the world, the foulnes of the church, this his loue: in him <hi>ergo</hi> ſhe is faire &amp; all faire: ſo is it ſaid:<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.29. 1. Ioh. 1.7.</note> that the bloode of Ieſu Chriſt the ſon of God clenſeth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al ſin: not <hi>ergo</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome but from al foulnes of ſin: in him <hi>ergo</hi> wee are fair and al fair. Al theſe propoſitions and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite like, they are the ſum of the goſpel, the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of grace, which concerne this faire loue of chriſt, the godly not in themſelues but in their Chriſt, not in their own frailties but in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23.</note> not in any imperfect perfection but in his perfect propitiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in his ſatiſpaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which hath anſwered iuſtice and ſwallowed iudgement ſo for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that their ſins ſhal neuer come in accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts but are &amp; ſhal be as cyphars &amp; this lones ſpots &amp; filthines are &amp; ſhal be ſo drowned,<note place="margin">Eſa. 1.18.</note> that they ſhall neuer be imputed but ſhe be euer reputed fair &amp; al fair according to this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>datio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of her why, but if chriſt ſhed not his precius blood to waſh hir al clear, how ſtands your expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,
<pb facs="tcp:4527:15"/>
that ſhe is fair and al fair in the bloode of her Chriſt? Whereunto I anſwere, as before I haue aunſwered, that Chriſt ſpent his precious blood, not to clenſe her from ſinne, but from all her ſinnes.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.9. Act. 4.12.</note> Inſomuch, that where ſhe is charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with none, ſhe oweth all the thanks to God in Ieſu Chriſt alone, who by himſelfe did (as hee was to that purpoſe appointed) offer not only <hi>7.</hi> times his bloode to remoue from this his loue her <hi>7.</hi> mortal ſins and no more (as diuers of our aduerſaries ſpeak too ſhort in the goſpel) &amp; that he therefore left her by due ſatisfaction, either of her owne perfourmance or of others for her to clenſe her ſelfe from the reſt: but all the verity and vertue of this commendation is onely and wholy and euer and of al and of al thinges moſt thankfully to be aſcribed to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Cipr. de caena dom. ſermo. pag. <hi>447.</hi> Bern. de paſ. dom. ſer. &amp; dom. in ramis palm. ſer. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> in whome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſhe is ſo al fair, that there are in her no ſpots to be found: none to be found, becauſe they are al purged away in his precious bloode, which hee ſpared not but ſpent for al her ſins. And indeede ſet aſide the blood of Chriſt, and his propitiation in any reſpect: if the church were left to clenſe her ſelfe from any ſinne and cannot bee all faire, vnleſſe ſhe do by due ſatisfaction perfourme the ſame, then is ſhe no way al faire, ſhee cannot bee without ſpot. For none of her obedience can bee ſufficient to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence God for the leſt ſin of al:<note place="margin">Baſ. int reg. monar. ca. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> which (being an infinit offence) cannot be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by her finite or rather faulting obedience: ſo
<pb facs="tcp:4527:15"/>
faultie? That although they dare talke of her fairenes, al fairnes, yea and of her ouerplus that way: of her works, of her merits of congruence, dignity and condignity, nay (more then al this) ſuperogatory: yet I ſay not only as <hi>Hugo Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalis</hi> (who beareth the name) doth note vpon the Pſalmes, that mans miſery it is, that hee knoweth not his merites (which prooues their faith of ſatiſfaction to bee all vncerteine: vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine and therefore no faith:<note place="margin">All our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries grant the concluſion.</note>) but alſo (as <hi>Ferus</hi> wel notes againſt the will of our aduerſaries v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes:</hi>) That man is miſerable who cannot better weigh what be his demerits: and account more truly of ſin, then as of a ſore that according to the meetered creede of our aduerſaries, by almeſgiuing or faſting or praieng or knocking of the breſt or by pilgrima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging or by aſperſion of water or epiſcopal bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction or by ſuch fancied meanes may be clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: Where the ſcripture in general deſcribeth ſin to be a ſore, ſo lothſome, that none coulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent this loue fair without ſpot in the eies of God but only Chriſt by waſhing her from al ſin in his precious bloode: whereunto therefore all the effect of this commendation is aſcribed. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though therfore the church be ſubiect to ſinne: to foulnes in this life: yet notwithſtanding ſhee is precious and pure: glorious, faire and all faire without ſpot in the eies of her God, whoſe eies be not, as the eies of fleſh and bloode (which are
<pb facs="tcp:4527:16"/>
deceiued:) but true and pure and do behould her pure becauſe purified in his owne deare ſonne, whoſe bloode doeth euer and alone couer all her ſpots and blemiſhes from him. In which reſpect yet, to ſatiſfie the naturall man and all ſuch as ſometimes yealde him the hearing: (as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaid of Chriſt, ſo ſay I of her:) we muſt diſtinguiſh <hi>inter oculum &amp; aurem:</hi> for <hi>ſi oculus at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendat, quid apparebat? Quomodo formoſus erat Chriſtus &amp;c.</hi> To the eie what did chriſt appear? How was he al faire or faire? For what ſaw the ey in Chriſt but blacknes and deformity? When his handes were ſpreade vppon the tree and he was put to deſpiſal among the wicked, to pains by his enemies: when he, that was to bee honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of al and could haue put an amaze and feare in the harts of al, yet was a contempt and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtocke to al? But we muſt (ſaith hee) diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh <hi>inter oculum &amp; aurem:</hi> for <hi>oculus</hi> did <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciaere Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infirmum, oculus foedum &amp;c.</hi> To the eye therefore Chriſt was weake, to the eye foul foule, becauſe miſerable, foule becauſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to dy a moſt ſhameful death: but yet <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> to the eare, he was <hi>Dei filius: auri formoſus, prae filijs hominum formoſus innotuit.</hi> To the eare hee was the ſon of God, to the eare he was fair and al fair: ſo ſay I of the church: ſhe is put to deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal and pains in the world: ſhe is no better then a ſtone of offence: ſhe is not fair but al foul: <hi>haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica, maligna, maculata</hi> with ſinne: and howe is
<pb facs="tcp:4527:16"/>
ſhe not charged by the wicked? But yet <hi>auri,</hi> to the eare, ſhe is the loue, the bride, the ſpouſe of Ieſu Chriſt: ſhe is his houſe, his temple, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, the very white of his eie: ſhee is (as heere you doe here) faire and all faire: And as for them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> otherwiſe iudge, (as multituds euer haue don and do now adaies) eſteeming the church by her outward ſtate &amp; other frailtes, they are ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as doe <hi>plus tribuere oculo qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oraculo, i. carnis ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſui quam verbo Dei:</hi> they aſcribe more to ſenſe then to faith, as Saint <hi>Bernarde</hi> ſpeakes. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe as Chriſt was <hi>niger oculis perſequenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, niger reputatione Herodis:</hi> and yet was <hi>formo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus confeſſione latronis, fide centurionis:</hi> black <hi>ergo</hi> in the eies of his perſecuting enimies, blacke in <hi>Herods</hi> eie: and yet fair and al fair to the theefe confeſſing, to the <hi>Centurion</hi> beleeuing: ſo the church this loue of our ſauior is carnal, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, foul, what leſſe then all foule in the eies of <hi>Turkes, Iewes, Epicures, Atheiſts, Papiſts,</hi> and al the wicked, where yet ſhe is no leſſe then faire and al fair in the eies of al the faithfull, who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing, doe by faith beholde her all faire in the blood of her ſpotles Chriſt: to end in a word: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the trueth of this her commendation where with I began: that ſhe is al faire and that there is in her no ſpot to be found.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
